We've touched on the concept of pipelining a few times before, but in this lecture we'll
apply the concept to processors.
First we'll learn how to take the single cycle processor and convert it to multi-cycle
using state elements.
Then we'll discuss pipelining and describe the necessary changes to the data path and
control logic.
As we discussed last time, the goal of a multi-cycle implementation is to break up the data path
into roughly equal sized stages such that each can be performed within one clock cycle.
Instructions will then take a varying amount of cycles to execute if they don't need to
participate in later stages.
Our implementation splits the data path into five stages.
Instruction fetch, instruction decode, execute, memory access, and writeback.
Let's investigate the five stages we've split our processor into.
The instruction fetch stage, abbreviated IF or F, both loads the current instruction
from memory and increments the program counter by four to move to the next instruction.
The second stage is instruction decode.
This stage decodes the instruction word and computes the control signals for the instruction,
including driving the read ports of the register file.
The ALU comes into play in stage three, execute.
As with our single cycle implementation, ALU operates on two source registers with our
format instructions, while for I-format instructions, the second operand is driven by the sign extended
immediate.
In this implementation, the execute stage also computes the target PC for branch instructions.
The memory stage performs the accesses to data memory.
Load instructions read from memory based on the address generated by base plus offset
in the ALU, while store instructions write to memory after a similar address calculation.
In addition, the memory stage sets the program counter to the target address if the branch
is to be taken, which is determined by the zero flag of the ALU.
Although this implementation resolves branches in the memory stage, they could also be resolved
earlier in the decode or execute stage.
It's all implementation specific.
The fifth and final stage writes the instructions result to the register file, if necessary.
The result is taken either from the ALU output or from the data memory, depending on the
instruction.
We did all of this work to prevent instruction by instruction wall clock delays from harming
our overall performance, so let's take a look at what we did.
Recall the critical path or the longest gate delay, which set our clock period, was likely
the load instruction with its many high latency operations.
Even if some instructions were resolved in less time, our cycle still had to encompass
the worst case.
Executing these three instructions takes three quite slow clock cycles.
On the other hand, with the multi-cycle implementation, the clock period is the longest of the stage
delays.
With five stages, the clock period will be at least T over 5.
But look, neither branch, unequal nor storeward need the writeback stage, so they can exit
early in return to fetch the next instruction.
We've just bettered up our program.
The eternal question in computer architecture is, can we do better?
In an ideal world, we can have the CPI of a single cycle instruction, yet the clock
period of a multi-cycle implementation.
Luckily we can pipeline our design and get both the cycle time and CPI that we want.
Now we're executing a portion of our instruction in each stage, and we've got overlapped execution
such that a different instruction can be in every stage.
Let's return to our buffet line analogy.
You're the blue person, waiting to add five entrees to your plate.
In a multi-cycle implementation, only one person can be at the buffet, and the next
person can come only when the first person has completed dishing up all five entrees.
This however is inefficient, as the five entrees are all separate and there's nothing technically
stopping five people from dishing up at a different entre at the same time.
For that reason, cafeterias naturally have pipelining and everyone moves in the same
direction.
Now the buffet can avoid a line of hangry people.
The five stages of our processor data path are the same.
As soon as instruction one is fetched and moves to the decode stage, then instruction
two can be fetched, and so on.
Until all five of the stages are doing meaningful work on different instructions.
There are three pipeline idealisms.
First, like in multi-cycle, all stages are uniform in delay.
No one stage dominates in delay, ensuring that the clock period is at the absolute minimum.
Second, all instructions perform the same set of actions and utilize all stages.
In our case, this ensures that all five parts of a pipeline are doing meaningful work and
not idled.
Third, there's no dependencies between instructions and different stages.
This would be similar to our buffet, where only one serving spoon was available for entre
and three, and they needed to share.
These dependencies are called hazards and we'll look at them in a future lecture.
Can we have all three?
Well, unfortunately not, but we have methods we can utilize to get close enough and realize
significant speedups.
Here's the challenge in front of us.
We want to support five different instructions in flight in any given cycle.
In terms of control, we need to remember control signals of multiple instructions at
different stages of the pipe.
As I hinted in the last slide, instructions may have dependencies.
These dependencies can be in data or control and may force the pipe to stall and insert
idle bubbles.
We'll discuss those in the next lecture.
Let's introduce pipeline registers between each of the stages.
These will serve two purposes.
One, they retain values needed in subsequent stages.
For an example, they retain the outputs from memory and the ALU result for the write back
stage.
Two, any values needed at a later stage are propagated downstream.
Take the store instruction.
The value to store is read from the RT register in the decode stage, but we don't use it
until the memory stage once we know the address we're writing it to.
So the 32-bit register value is simply passed from the decode execute pipeline register
to the execute memory register during the execute stage.
Keep in mind that these register values can't just be passed along in zero time.
The instruction that came before the store is currently in the memory access stage and
those would collide.
Registers must keep all their data together as they traverse the pipeline.
Okay, it's time for some visuals.
First we'll consider an add instruction.
In the first cycle, the instruction is fetched and the PC is incremented.
In cycles two and three, the registers are read and operated on by the ALU.
Everything happens in cycle four as an R4MAT instruction doesn't access data memory.
But in the fifth cycle, the sum is written back to the register file.
Now let's do a day in the life of a load instruction next.
The first cycle is the same as the add instruction.
In cycle two, source registers are read and the immediate offset is sign extended.
In cycle three, the memory address is computed by the ALU.
In cycle four, the address is used to read from data memory.
And finally in cycle five, the value read from memory is written back to the register
file.
Now let's see what these look like when pipeline together.
After the add instruction is fetched, it moves to the decode stage while simultaneously
the load instruction is fetched.
It then executes while the load decodes.
These two instructions move through the pipeline in back to back stages.
The requirement to have control signals at the right time has not changed.
But now that we could have a different instruction at each stage, the control signals of each
instruction need to be kept bundled in pipeline registers with the instruction, therefore.
In our example, all control bits are calculated in the decode stage.
Let's bundle control bits and label them for the stage they're needed, and then keep
them flowing forward in lockstep, stage by stage, as the instruction moves to the right
back stage.
Decode has to pass most of them to the execute stage, but the signals needed for execute
don't need to be passed to memory.
Let's take the memory read and memory write flags.
They're computed in decode, but not used until memory, so they must be passed forward
twice and no more because they're not needed for write back.
Let's add the registered control signals to our diagram and make it even more complete.
It's once again time to check your knowledge with a simple exercise.
Say you're building a processor data path, and your physical design results show the
delays of each stage as shown.
If this were a single cycle processor, what would the instructions per second be?
Please pause the video and work through this as if it were a homework question.
First we find the clock period by summing the delays for a total of one millisecond.
Since this is single cycle, the IPC is one.
So the instructions per second would be the number of one millisecond clock cycles that
fit in one second, which is one divided by one millisecond or one thousand instructions
per second.
What throughput could you achieve with a pipelined implementation instead?
Pause and work through it as if it were a class exercise.
Since your clock can't be faster than your slowest stage, the clock period must be 350
microseconds.
The IPC can be computed as the number of instructions executed divided by the number
of cycles it takes to execute them, which is the number of instructions plus four.
For large programs, the plus four in the denominator effectively vanishes.
This results approximately in an IPC of one, the same as the single cycle processor.
And some quick math on our wall clock time shows that we can do approximately 2,857 instructions
per second.
This is a significant speed up over our single cycle implementation.